<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fearefull example, shewed vpon a periured person Who on the 14, of this present moneth of May being condemned for periury, in the honourable Court of Starre Chamber: did there desperatly stabbe himselfe. Containing a notable warning to all common baylors.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19965</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119186</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854393</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854393</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09697)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1554:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fearefull example, shewed vpon a periured person Who on the 14, of this present moneth of May being condemned for periury, in the honourable Court of Starre Chamber: did there desperatly stabbe himselfe. Containing a notable warning to all common baylors.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Allde] for Thomas Nelson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1591]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Text dated: 14. of May. 1591.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pitcher, John, d. 1591.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Court of Star Chamber.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19812:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 74 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:19812:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 74 -->
            <head>¶ The fearefull example of God <hi>showed on a periured Perſon, who at the Starre</hi> Chamber receiuing ſentence in that caſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided: diſperately ſtabbed himſelfe <hi>on Friday being the 14. of May.</hi> 1591.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Herunto ſhould I liken this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? Why whereunto ſhould I liken this generation, but vnto that generation in our Sauiours time vpon the earth, whome he (the onely wiſdome) compareth vnto Children playing in the ſtreets, to whom their fellowes crye, We haue piped vnto you, and you haue not daunced: we haue mounrned vnto you, and ye haue not wept: yea to this generation, we may againe ſay, as he to that: Woe be to thee hard harted people, woe be to thee obdurat na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for if the wonders had been ſhown in <hi>Tire</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> which haue beene ſhowen in thee, they would long ſince haue repented in Sacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth and aſhes. How many of our fellowes, or rather fathers whome we ought to follow, haue cheerefully ſung foorth the eternall reſt of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19812:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 75 -->
their ſoules, by the witnes of their vpright con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, hauing liu'd chriſtianly and left ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye this Tabernacle: whoſe remouing from vs but few regarde, veryfying the wiſemans woords. The righteous dyeth, and no man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth in his hart it is too lamentable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member. How many againe haue in their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable examples mourned vnto vs? ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing (bewitcht through Poperie) by trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, poiſon of their own preparations, hauing (through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> omnipotencie of him that ſhadowes his annointed) the edge of their own Swoords turned to their own throats: others for barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous murders and impious fellonies: other through ſubbornacions, forgeries, periuries, brought to infamous, yet deſerued reproches: ſo that numberleſſe is the number of theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable mourners, whoſe example can nothing terrifie this peruerſe age: The iudgements of God before time hath beene ſtretched largelye out againſt the rabble of the wicked, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt periurie, he hath in all ages, and at this day ſhowen deſerued vengeance.</p>
            <p>For vpon Friday being the 14. of May, in this caſe he affoorded a manifeſt example at the Starre Chamber, on a deſperate periured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, named Iohn Pitcher, who being with his conſort found guilty of periurye, was adiudged to looſe his eares vpon the Pillories at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter and London.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19812:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 75 -->For the circumſtance, that the worlde maye note their merite, it was thus: A priſoner are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted for a lawfull debt, the action being two thouſand markes, he was driuen to produce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall bayle, that is, two men of good account: this Pitcher and his companion, attired the one Gentleman like, the other Merchant like: being hired to baile the priſoner, turned their names and places of their dwelling: this Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher calling himſelfe Maiſter Downes, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that he was ten pounds in the Q. Bookes, and of good woorſhip in his Country: the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman indeed whoſe name he challenged, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well knowne to be of no leſſe eſtate: heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they baile the priſoner, defeate the Creditor, themſelues beeing of no eſteeme: and leauing a copper Chaine for one of golde, they embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced likewiſe the Diuell for God: yet he that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth ſuch diſſemblers, brought foorth theſe two counterfeites, who appearing before the right honourable the Lord Chauncellor, the Lord Archbiſhop his grace of Caunterburye, the two Lord cheefe Iuſtices, and the reſt of that Court, had ſentence as is aforeſaide: and commaundement was giuen to the warden of the Fleete, foorthwith to ſee the execution doone: but as they were carrying from the Starre Chamber, euen hard at the doore this deſperate Pitcher drew out his knife, and giuing himſelf two wounds in the breſt, fell downe: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19812:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 76 -->
the Lord Chauncellor and the reſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly commaunded his wounds ſhould be ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, which he obſtinatelye refuſed: therefore their honors appointed a diuine to be ſent him for his ſoules comfort and that he ſhould be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly held while his wounds were ſearched for his bodies health. O defexiles charitie, O ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and chriſtian pitie.</p>
            <p>But beholde the iuſt iudgement of God vpon this party, the better to make his odious offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſeene manifeſt &amp; to be apparent to many other, he made his owne conſciente witnes againſt him, that he was woorthy of death, when with his own hands he attempted to ſtrike the fatall ſtrokes that might ſuddenly haue ſhortned his own life: and this he choſe rather to perfourm by the perſwaſion of his owne conſcience, then to ſuſtaine the ſhame which the Law hath iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly awarded for ſo deteſtable an offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And yet contrarye to the expectation of himſelfe or thoſe that were eye witneſſes of this fearfull exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, his wounds being afterward ſearched and dreſt, were not found deadly but recouerable, ſo that he is now reaſonably amended, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth cloſe priſoner in the Fleete with his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther companion, vntil ſuch time as it ſhal pleaſe her Maieſties moſt honourable Counſell to commaund execution according to their former iudgements. Which is appointed to be doone foorth with.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19812:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 76 -->Now if this mournefull act might moue the reſt of this generation, who ſell the innocent for ſiluer, and the righteous for a reward: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting iuſtice into woormewood, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into gall: happy were they that brought theſe euill ones to light, and happy this fearfull example, for all Petyfoggers, Suborners, Knights of the Poſts, and all the vncleane ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell of vnchriſtened periurers, who by ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and forſwearing, bragging and out coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing, abuſe the Iuſtices, oppreſſe their poore Clients, and for a little peece of Siluer like <hi>Iudas,</hi> ſinne in betraying the innocent, ſinne in betraying of their own ſoules, ſinne in deſpairing of Gods grace, or preſuming of his goodnes, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temning his iudgements: whoſe hart (O Lord) conuert, or according to thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, teare them as a hungrye Lyon dooth his praye: for they ſhame not to ſaye, thou art like them becauſe of thy Long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. <hi>Amen Lord Ieſu come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
